<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page name="overview/requirements">
    <summary>
		Sparx is completely application server and platform neutral. All of the Sparx's many features are available in
        any Servlet-compliant application server like WebLogic, Websphere, Tomcat, and Resin. Sparx can work both with or
        without EJBs. Sparx's main requirement is the Java Developer's Kit (JDK). You can
        choose the Sun Java SDK, the IBM Java SDK, or any other variety that you prefer, as long as it complies with
        Java 1.2 or above.
        <ul>
            <li>You can obtain Sun's Java SDK from <a href="http://java.sun.com/">http://java.sun.com</a>.</li>
            <li>You can find IBM's Java SDK at <a href="http://www.ibm.com/java">http://www.ibm.com/java</a>.</li>
        </ul>
    </summary>

	<section heading="General Requirements">
        <table class="data" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" width="100%">
            <tr class="data_head">
                <th class="data">Category</th>
                <th class="data">Requirements</th>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">Operating System</td>
                <td class="data">Any platform that supports JDK 1.2 or above (e.g. Windows NT/2000/XP, Unix, Linux, Mac).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">Database</td>
                <td class="data">Any relational or object database that has a JDBC 2.0 driver (e.g. Oracle, Sybase, SQL Server).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">Application Server</td>
                <td class="data">Any application server that supports the Java Servlet 2.2 or above specification (Weblogic, Websphere, Resin, Tomcat, etc).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">IDE</td>
                <td class="data">Use any IDE or plain text editor.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">Object Services Protocol</td>
                <td class="data">Choose from CORBA, EJB, RMI, SOAP, DCOM or other object services.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data" valign="top">
                <td class="data">Process Model</td>
                <td class="data">Use any variety of process models like waterfall, RAD, JAD, XP (Extreme Programming), and other lightweight development processes.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
	</section>

    <section heading="Database Requirements">
        Our Developer Kit for evaluation is bundled with several sample applications. The two simpler sample applications,
        called <i>hello</i> and <i>library</i>, can be run using the bundled (free) HSQL Java database.
        <p/>
        One of the larger samples is Cura,
        a web based project management application for demonstration purposes. If you plan to evaluate Cura you will
        need to install Oracle (version 8 or newer) on a server and make it available for access by the server that will
        have the Sparx Developer Kit installed. You can choose to install Oracle on the same server as the Sparx
        Developer Kit provided it has the resources to handle both an application server and a database server.
    </section>

    <section heading="Integrated Development Environment (IDE) Requirements">
        You can also install a complete Java integrated development environment (IDE) for developing Sparx
        applications. Installation of such a development environment is, of course, strictly a personal preference
        and is <i>completely optional</i>. Sparx does not require nor endorse any particular Java IDE but will work
        with any IDE or text editor that you might wish to use while developing applications.
        If you choose to optionally install an IDE, take a look at:
        <ul>
            <li>IBM's VisualAge for Java</li>
            <li>JBuilder Community Edition</li>
            <li>IDEA's IntelliJ</li>
        </ul>
    </section>

	<section heading="Open-source (free) Libraries used by Sparx">
	<ul>
		<li><link http="jakarta.apache.org">Jakarta Ant 1.4.1</link> or above</li>
		<li><link http="jakarta.apache.org">Jakarta Log4J 1.1</link> or above</li>
		<li><link http="jakarta.apache.org">Jakarta ORO 2.0</link> or above</li>
		<li><link http="xml.apache.org">Apache Xerces 1.4</link> or above</li>
		<li><link http="xml.apache.org">Apache Xalan 2.1</link> or above</li>
	</ul>
	</section>
</page>