<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page name="xif/datatypes">
	<summary>
		Datatypes are created to help maintain a RDBMS-neutral and consistent data dictionary.
	</summary>

	<section heading="Overview of Datatypes">
	<ul>
		<li>Datatypes should be considered "column templates" that allow a programmer to specify a column type and are created using the &lt;datatype&gt; tag.</li>
		<li>Datatypes are completely schema dependent but may be reused across applications. This means that the basic templating system (SchemaDoc to XSLT generator) does not have any "built-in" datatypes.</li>
		<li>Datatypes may be inherited from other datatypes, allowing better reuse and object-orientation in relational databases.</li>
		<li>Datatypes easily generate and maintains a database-independent data dictionary.</li>
		<li>Datatypes provide their SQL DDL using the &lt;sqldefn&gt; tag (multiple &lt;sqldefn&gt; tags may be used to provide DDL specifications for a variety of databases).</li>
		<li>Datatypes provide Java object-relational mapping (DAL) using the
			<ul>
				<li>&lt;java-type&gt; (for primitives) and </li>
				<li>&lt;java-class&gt; (for normal classes) elements. The &lt;java-type&gt; element is optional, but the &lt;java-class&gt; element is required if a Java DAL will be generated for a schema.</li>
				<li>&lt;java-date-format-instance&gt; element should also be provided if the datatype being defined will generate a date or datetime object</li>
			</ul>
			</li>
		<li>Datatypes are usually simple types like "text", "integer", or "float".</li>
		<li>More complex types like "duration" can be created by using the &lt;composite&gt; tag allowing a single datatype to automatically generate multiple columns in tables.</li>
	</ul>
	</section>

	<channel xsdn-src="xif-xsdn" xsdn-element="/xif/datatype" describe-children="/*"/>
	<p/>
	<channel heading="Basic Text Datatype Definition" type="xml-source" include="../../../cura/WEB-INF/schema/datatypes.xml" element="/schema/datatype[@name = 'text']"/>
	<p/>
	<channel heading="Numeric Datatype Definition" type="xml-source" include="../../../cura/WEB-INF/schema/datatypes.xml" element="/schema/datatype[@name = 'integer']"/>
	<p/>
	<channel heading="Date Datatype Definition" type="xml-source" include="../../../cura/WEB-INF/schema/datatypes.xml" element="/schema/datatype[@name = 'date']"/>
	<p/>
	<channel heading="Composite Datatype Definition" type="xml-source" include="../../../cura/WEB-INF/schema/datatypes.xml" element="/schema/datatype[@name = 'duration']"/>
</page>