<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page name="xaf/configuration">
	<summary>
		The XAF favors XML storage of properties instead of using Java properties
		files. The ConfigurationManager class allows multiple properties to be
		defined in a single XML file, complete with variable replacements and the
		ability to create single-property or multiple property (list) items. Optionally,
		any property name could refer to <link page="xaf/value-sources">value sources</link>
		as part of the definition of a property so that the value of a property can become
		dynamic and be computed each time the property is used (in case the value of the
		property is based on a servlet request or session variable or some other application-defined
		business rule).
	</summary>

	<section heading="Examples">
		<channel type="xml-source">
			<property name="system.projects-root" value="C:/Projects"/>
			<property name="framework.root-path" value="${system.projects-root}/Framework"/>
			<property name="app.project-root" value="${system.projects-root}/cura"/>
			<properties name="framework.ace.transform">
				<property name="dml" value="${framework.ace.xslt-path}/article-transform.xsl"/>
				<property name="tpml" value="${framework.ace.xslt-path}/test-plan-transform.xsl"/>
			</properties>

			<property name="app.root-url" value="${create-app-url:/}"/>
			<property name="app.page.1" value="${create-app-url:/page1}"/>
			<property name="app.page.2" value="${create-app-url:/page2}"/>
		</channel>
		<br/>
		Basically, a property element has two portions -- a name and a value. A name is always
		a static text string but the value can be one of the following:
		<ul>
			<li>
				A static text or numeric value (one that does not change over time). In the
				example above, the <i>system.projects-root</i> property is a static text property.
			</li>
			<li>
				A text or numeric value that should be computed using other properties but as soon as the value
				is evaluated for the first time, its value becomes static. In the
				example above, the <i>framework.root-path</i> property is a text property whose
				value depends upon the <i>system.projects-root</i> property.
			</li>
			<li>
				A text or numeric value that should be computed using other properties or
				<link page="xaf/value-sources">value sources</link>. These kinds of
				properties will never have a static value and will be computed each time the
				property is referenced. In the
				example above, the <i>app.root-url</i> property is a dynamic property because
				it refers to a single value source whose value depends upon the execution
				environment of the servlet.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<channel xsdn-element="/xaf/configuration" describe-children="/*"/>

	<channel
		heading="Extended examples (standard configuration.xml file)"
		type="xml-source"
		include="../../../cura/WEB-INF/configuration.xml"/>
</page>
