<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page name="downloads">
    <summary>
        The full Sparx Application Platform Release <sparx-build-version/> can be downloaded for a free 30-day evaluation period.
        <p/>
        Please <link page="overview/requirements">review the requirements</link> first, make sure you have a <a href="http://java.sun.com">JDK</a> installed,
        then click one of the links below to download and install the evaluation kit.
        <p/>
        <table class="data" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
            <tr class="data_head">
                <th class="data">Kit</th>
                <th class="data">Size</th>
                <th class="data">Instructions</th>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <td class="data"><b><sparx-bin-kit-link-zip/></b></td>
                <td class="data" align="center"><nobr>5 mb</nobr></td>
                <td class="data">
                    Binaries only (no app server, samples, or documentation).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <td class="data"><b><sparx-eval-kit-link-zip/></b></td>
                <td class="data" align="center"><nobr>30 mb</nobr></td>
                <td class="data">
                	Complete Sparx evaluation kit for Windows. Includes <a href="http://www.caucho.com">Resin</a> application server, Sparx binaries,
                	introductory whitepaper, developer guides, and sample applications.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <td class="data"><b><sparx-eval-kit-link-tgz/></b></td>
                <td class="data" align="center"><nobr>30 mb</nobr></td>
                <td class="data">
                	Complete Sparx evaluation kit for Linux, UNIX, and MacOS. Includes <a href="http://www.caucho.com">Resin</a> application server, Sparx binaries,
                	introductory whitepaper, developer guides, and sample applications.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </summary>

    <section heading="Tutorials and Documentation">
        Sparx includes hundreds of pages of both online (HTML) and offline (PDF) documentation. To get the most out of the
        sample applications described below, please review the documents described below and follow along with the
        samples either <link page="samples">online</link> or on your own servers.
        <p/>
        <table class="data" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
            <tr class="data_head">
                <th class="data"> </th>
                <th class="data">Document</th>
                <th class="data">Samples Covered</th>
                <th class="data">Purpose</th>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Netspective_Sparx_White_Paper.pdf"><nobr><b>Sparx Introduction (White Paper)</b></nobr></a></td>
                <td class="data">All</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Introduces you to all of the major concepts in Sparx. Download and read this document before
                    delving into the Sparx Developers Guides below.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Sparx_Developers_Guide_Volume_I.pdf"><nobr><b>Sparx Developers Guide Volume I</b></nobr></a></td>
                <td class="data">Hello, Library</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Describes the two primary means for evaluating Sparx -- online and offline. Furthermore, it
                    explains how to install Sparx onto your local servers and how to peruse the source code online.
                    It then introduces Sparx by describing most of the functionality and walking the reader through the
                    development of two full-scale sample applications <i>hello</i> and <i>library</i> (Hello World and
                    the Sparx Library).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Sparx_Developers_Guide_Volume_II.pdf"><nobr><b>Sparx Developers Guide Volume II</b></nobr></a></td>
                <td class="data">Cura</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Provides examples that demonstrate the advanced functions available in Sparx. This is primarily
                    done by walking the reader through the implementation of a sophisticated project management application
                    called <i>Cura</i>.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>

</page>