<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page name="samples">
    <summary>
        The utility of any application framework can be discovered three ways. The first is introductory material that
        explains what the framework does. The second is detailed API documentation and usage patterns. The third, and
        perhaps the most important, is by looking at sample applications and actual code. This page describes the
        many sample applications provided with the <link page="overview/eval-kit">Sparx Evaluation Kit</link>,
        all of which are also available online.
    </summary>

    <section heading="Tutorials and Documentation">
        Sparx includes hundreds of pages of both online (HTML) and offline (PDF) documention. To get the most ouf the
        sample applications described below, please review the documents described below and follow along. Click
        <a href="Getting_Started_With_Sparx.pdf">here</a> to learn about how to review the source code for the sample
        applications online if you have not downloaded the <link page="overview/eval-kit">Sparx Evaluation Kit</link>.
        <p/>
        <table class="data" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3">
            <tr class="data_head">
                <th class="data"> </th>
                <th class="data">Document</th>
                <th class="data">Samples Covered</th>
                <th class="data">Purpose</th>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Getting_Started_With_Sparx.pdf">Getting Started with Sparx</a></td>
                <td class="data">All</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Describes the two primary means for evaluating Sparx -- online and offline. Furthermore, it
                    explains how to install Sparx onto your local servers and how to peruse the source code online.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Sparx_Tutorial.pdf">Sparx Tutorial</a></td>
                <td class="data">Hello, Library</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Introduces Sparx by describing most of the functionality and walking the reader through the
                    development of two full-scale sample applications <i>hello</i> and <i>library</i> (Hello World and
                    Sparx Collection).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr class="data">
                <th class="data"><image src="pdf-logo-sm.gif"/></th>
                <td class="data"><a href="Advanced_Sparx_Tutorial.pdf">Advanced Sparx Tutorial</a></td>
                <td class="data">Cura</td>
                <td class="data">
                    Provides examples that demonstrate the advanced functions available in Sparx. This is primarily
                    done by walking the reader through the implementation of sophisticated project management application
                    called <i>Cura</i>.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>

	<summarize-children heading="Sparx Samples Available for Online or Offline evaluation"/>

</page>